Guide to the Edwin Richard Weinerman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Personal Papers and Miscellaneous, Series V; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - program from E. R. Weinerman's graduation from the Harvard University School of Public Health, 1948 (Box 68, Folder 9)
  - papers re: Weinerman's military service, 1942-1947, 1952, 1962 (Box 68, Folder 10)
  - papers re: Weinerman's veterans benefits, 1946-1948 (Box 68, Folder 11)
  - papers re: medical licensure, 1942-1943, 1946, 1948-1949, 1955-1964, 1967 (Box 68, Folder 12)
  - papers re: medical partnership between E. R. Weinerman, F. M. Epstein, and E. Kahn, 1953, 1955, 1957, 1960, 1962 (Box 68, Folder 13)
  - Weinerman's farewell letter to patients and replies, 1962 (Box 68, Folder 14)
  - papers re: Weinerman's departure from Berkeley, 1962 (Box 68, Folder 15)
  - papers re: E. R. Weinerman's house in El Cerrito, California (Box 68, Folder 16)
  - papers re: move from El Cerrito to New Haven (Box 68, Folder 17)
  - papers re: Pierson College and Weinerman's advisees (Box 68, Folder 18)
  - papers re: Ridge Top Club (Box 68, Folder 19)
  - papers re: E. R. Weinerman's Social Security Account (Box 69, Folder 20)
  - Christmas letter from the Weinermans, 1962 (Box 69, Folder 21)
  - correspondence and papers re: various Yale University funds (Box 69, Folder 22)
  - correspondence and papers re: Yale Class of 1938 and Yale Alumni Fund, 1951, 1961-1969 (Box 69, Folder 23)
  - papers re: Yale Faculty Club and Yale Newcomers Club (Box 69, Folder 24)
  - papers re: Beth Israel Hospital Medical Alumni Association (Box 69, Folder 25)
  - papers re: Georgetown University Class of 1942 (Box 69, Folder 26)
  - papers re: Bookshelf of America, Inc., 1963-1968 (Box 69, Folder 27)
  - Lion's Club "Certificates of Appreciation" (Box 69, Folder 28)
  - travel expense reports and vouchers, 1963-1965 (Box 69, Folder 29)
  - travel expense reports and vouchers, 1966-1969 (Box 69, Folder 30-31)
  - bills, invoices, and receipts (Box 69, Folder 32-34)
  - American Express invoices (Box 69, Folder 35)
  - miscellaneous (Box 69, Folder 36-37)
  - Correspondence (Box 69A)
- Additional Materials, 1908-1980; Accession 1981-M-001
  - Socio-economic factors in health and disease
    - General (Box 70)
      - State of the nation's health (Box 70)
    - Mortality studies (Box 70)
      - Infant mortality (Box 70)
    - Morbidity studies (Box 70)
      - Selective Service (Box 70)
      - Disability and chronic illness (Box 70)
    - Environmental factors in health (Box 70)
      - Economic status and health (Box 70)
      - Occupation and health (Box 70)
      - Nutrition and health (Box 70)
      - Housing and health (Box 71)
      - Rural life and health (Box 71)
      - Urbanization and health (Box 71)
      - Population and characteristics (Box 71)
        - Problems of the aged (Box 71)
        - Status of women (Box 71)
        - Population mobility (Box 71)
      - Racial factors in health (Box 71)
      - Health and war (Box 72)
      - Cultural factors, sociological (Box 72)
    - Need for health services (Box 72)
  - Medical care economics (Box 72)
    - General (Box 72)
    - Receipt of medical care (Box 72)
      - Rural medical care (Box 72)
      - Costs of medical care (Box 72)
        - Costs of hospital care (Box 72)
      - Costs of illness (Box 72)
      - Expenditures for medical care (Box 72)
  - Medical care personnel (Box 72)
    - General supply and distribution of medical care personnel (Box 72)
    - Physicians (Box 73)
      - Income of physicians (Box 73)
      - General practice (Box 73)
      - Doctor-patient relationships (Box 73)
      - Specialization (Box 73)
      - Professional liability (Box 73)
      - Medical students (Box 73)
      - Hospital-M.D. relationships (Box 73)
    - Nurses (Box 73)
    - Public health personnel (Box 73)
    - Medical administrators (Box 73)
    - Quacks (Box 73)
    - Non-M.D. health personnel (Box 73)
  - Medical care facilities (Box 73)
    - General supply and distribution of facilities (Box 73)
    - Hospitals
      - Hospitals, general (Box 73)
      - General hospitals (Box 73)
      - Special hospitals (Box 73)
      - Licensure and standards (Box 73)
      - Surveys (Box 74)
      - Construction (Box 74)
      - Administration (Box 74)
      - Progressive care (Box 74)
      - Emergency service (Box 74)
      - Teaching hospitals (Box 74)
    - Clinics (Box 74)
    - Health centers (Box 74)
      - Poverty neighborhoods (Box 74)
      - Rural health centers (Box 74)
    - Laboratories (Box 74)
    - Nursing homes (Box 74)
    - Psychiatric facilities (Box 74)
  - Organization of services and facilities
    - General (Box 74)
      - Individual plans (Box 75)
        - Rip Van Winkle Clinic (Box 75)
    - Group practice, general (Box 75)
      - Legal aspects (Box 75)
      - Prepaid group practice (Box 75)
      - Individual plans (Box 75)
        - Rip Van Winkle Clinic (Box 75)
      - Voluntary medical care programs-United States
        - General (Box 78)
        - Cash indemnity plans (Box 78)
        - Non-profit service (Box 78)
          - Blue Cross/Connecticut Blue Cross (Box 78)
          - Medical Society plans (Box 78)
            - California Physicians Service (Box 78)
            - Connecticut Medical Service (Box 78)
            - Group Health Insurance, New York (Box 78)
          - Group health plans, general (Box 79)
            - Group Health Cooperative, Seattle (Box 79)
            - Group Health Association, Washington, D.C. (Box 79)
            - Community Health Association, Detroit (Box 79)
            - Community Health Association, Santa Rosa (Box 79)
            - Group Health Association, Sault Ste. Marie (Box 79)
            - Community Health Services, Saskatchewan (Box 79)
            - Cooperative health plans (Box 79)
          - Community health plans (Box 79)
            - Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York (Box 79)
            - Kaiser-Permanente Plan (Box 79)
            - Los Angeles Community Medical Center (Box 79)
            - Medical care plans, California (Box 79)
            - Community Health Foundation, Cleveland (Box 79)
          - Private group clinics-Ross-Loos Medical Group (Box 80)
        - Labor and management plans (Box 80)
          - Labor and health (Box 80)
          - Medical care plans under collective bargaining (Box 80)
          - Union medical care plans (Box 80)
            - UMWA plans (Box 80)
            - UAW plans (Box 80)
            - ILWU plans (Box 80)
          - Labor health centers (Box 80)
            - Labor Health Institute (Box 81)
        - Industrial medical care plans (Box 81)
        - Farm Security Administration plans (Box 81)
        - Individual practice plans (Box 81)
        - University plans (Box 81)
    - Regionalization
      - Bingham Plan (Box 75)
      - Rochester Plan (Box 75)
      - Regional Medical Program (RMP) (Box 75)
    - Home care, general (Box 75)
      - Individual plans (Box 76)
        - Montefiore Plan (Box 76)
    - Health maintenance services (Box 76)
    - Homemaker service (Box 76)
    - Private medical practice (Box 76)
    - Panel plans (Box 76)
    - Health care planning (Box 76)
  - Medical care administration
    - General (Box 76)
      - Administration of medical care by health departments (Box 76)
      - Organizational structures in medical care programs (Box 76)
      - Administrative procedures in medical care plans (Box 76)
    - Financial aspects in medical care programs (Box 76)
      - Methods of payment (Box 76)
    - Services and benefits in medical care programs (Box 76)
    - Utilization data (Box 76)
    - Enrollment and coverage (Box 77)
    - Morbidity and mortality in prepaid plans (Box 77)
    - Prevention in medical care plans (Box 77)
    - Quality of medical care (Box 77)
      - Quality studies (Box 77)
      - Quality controls (Box 77)
    - Evaluation of medical care (Box 77)
      - Medical audit (Box 77)
      - Evaluation of prepaid plans (Box 77)
      - Sampling methodology (Box 77)
      - Utilization review (Box 77)
      - Data processing and automation (Box 77)
    - Legal aspects of medical care (Box 77)
  - Compulsory medical care programs-United States
    - General (Box 81)
      - Planning for national health insurance (Box 81)
    - Compulsory plans in operation (Box 81)
    - Workmen's Compensation (Box 81)
    - Disability insurance, general (Box 81)
      - State, California (Box 81)
  - Public medical care
    - General (Box 81)
    - For the needy (Box 81)
      - Baltimore and Maryland plans (Box 81)
      - Washington State program (Box 81)
      - California (Box 81)
      - Medicaid (Box 81)
    - Special groups (Box 82)
      - Veterans (Box 82)
      - EMIC (Box 82)
      - Crippled Children's Service (Box 82)
      - Schools (Box 82)
      - Migratory Farm Workers Health Service (Box 82)
        - Migratory farm workers health problems (Box 82)
      - Aged-Medicare (Box 82)
      - Military (Box 82)
      - Federal/state employees (Box 82)
      - Indians (Box 82)
    - Special diseases-chronic diseases (Box 82)
    - Public medical care for all (Box 82)
  - Foreign medical care programs
    - General (Box 82)
    - Individual countries (Box 82)
      - Czechoslovakia (Box 82)
      - France (Box 82)
      - Israel (Box 82)
      - Poland (Box 82)
      - Hungary (Box 83)
      - Yugoslavia (Box 83)
      - Belgium (Box 83)
      - Germany (Box 83)
      - Great Britain and Scotland (Box 83)
      - Canada/Saskatchewan (Box 83)
      - U.S.S.R. (Box 83)
      - Japan (Box 83)
      - New Zealand (Box 83)
      - Latin America (Box 83)
      - Scandinavian countries (Box 83)
      - Germany (Box 83)
  - Proposals and legislation
    - General opinions and attitudes (Box 84)
      - A.M.A. and related views (Box 84)
      - Liberal medical views (Box 84)
      - Labor and other lay views (Box 84)
      - Public opinion polls (Box 84)
    - Medical care proposals (Box 84)
      - General (Box 84)
      - International (Box 84)
      - National (Box 84)
      - State (Box 84)
      - Regional (Box 84)
      - Local (Box 84)
    - Legislation (Box 85)
      - General (Box 85)
      - National (Box 85)
        - Medical care for the aged under Social Security (Medicare) (Box 85)
        - National health insurance (Box 85)
          - Wagner Bills (Box 85)
          - Hill Bill (Box 85)
          - Taft Bill (Box 85)
          - Ives-Flanders Bill (Box 85)
        - Heart disease, cancer, and stroke (Box 85)
        - Comprehensive health planning (Box 85)
        - Demonstration cities (HUD) (Box 85)
        - Title 19-Medicaid (Box 85)
        - Federal granting agencies (Box 85)
        - Hill-Burton Program (Box 85)
      - State (Box 85)
        - California State Employees Health Program (Box 85)
        - California State Hospital Bill of 1960 (Box 85)
        - Connecticut state legislation (Box 85)
  - Special services
    - General (Box 86)
      - Psychiatric care in health insurance (Box 86)
    - Chronic disease control (Box 86)
      - Chronic and convalescent care/care of mental illness (Box 86)
      - Chronic care facilities-Maimonides Health Center for the Chronic Sick (Box 86)
      - Geriatrics (Box 86)
      - Medical care plans for the aged (non-public) (Box 86)
    - Rehabilitation-Kabat-Kaiser Institute (Box 86)
    - Social Security (Box 86)
    - Public welfare (Box 86)
    - Nursing/nursing and health insurance (Box 86)
    - Dental care (Box 86)
      - Prepaid dental care (Box 87)
    - Medical social service (Box 87)
    - Drugs-drugs in prepaid plans (Box 87)
    - Preventive medicine (Box 87)
      - Periodic health examinations (Box 87)
      - Multiple screenings (Box 87)
      - Health maintenance (Box 87)
    - Environmental health (Box 91)
      - Industrial hygiene (Box 91)
      - Sanitation (Box 91)
      - Accident prevention (Box 91)
      - Abortion (Box 91)
      - Disaster control (Box 91)
      - Nutrition (Box 91)
      - Automobile problems (Box 91)
      - Water pollution (Box 91)
      - Radiation (Box 91)
      - Air pollution (Box 91)
  - Social aspects of medicine
    - General (Box 87)
    - Teaching of social medicine (Box 88)
      - Teaching of preventive medicine (Box 88)
      - Family or community medicine in medical education (Box 88)
      - Bibliographies in social medicine (Box 88)
    - Social factors affecting health (Box 88)
      - Social pathology (Box 88)
        - Smoking and health (Box 88)
        - Air pollution (Box 88)
        - Food additives (Box 88)
        - Alcoholism (Box 88)
        - Obesity (Box 88)
        - Drug use (Box 88)
    - Social aspects of diagnosis and treatment (Box 88)
    - Social factors (Box 88)
      - Rheumatic fever (Box 88)
      - Heart disease (Box 89)
      - Cancer (Box 89)
      - Tuberculosis (Box 89)
      - Mental illness (Box 89)
        - Tension and anxiety-social factors (Box 89)
        - Suicide (Box 89)
      - Chronic respiratory disease (Box 89)
      - Cerebrovascular disease (Box 89)
    - Social science in medicine (Box 89)
    - Social medicine research (Box 89)
      - Health service research (Box 89)
      - Patient care research (Box 90)
      - Research in medical practice (Box 90)
      - Medical care surveys (Box 90)
      - International medical care research (Box 90)
      - Legal medicine (Box 90)
  - Professional education and research
    - General (Box 90)
    - Medical education (Box 90)
    - Training of public health physicians (Box 90)
    - Medical research, general (Box 90)
    - Training in medical care administration (Box 90)
    - Training for primary care (Box 90)
  - Public health
    - General (Box 90)
    - Administration (Box 90)
      - National public health administration (Box 90)
      - State public health administration (Box 91)
        - State of California (Box 91)
      - Local public health administration (Box 91)
      - Public health laws (Box 91)
      - World health (Box 91)
    - Maternal and child health (Box 91)
      - Maternal health (Box 91)
      - Child health (Box 91)
      - Birth control (Box 91)
      - School health (Box 91)
    - Environmental health (Box 91)
      - Industrial hygiene (Box 91)
      - Sanitation (Box 91)
      - Accident prevention (Box 91)
      - Disaster control (Box 91)
      - Abortion (Box 91)
      - Nutrition (Box 91)
      - Automobile problems (Box 91)
      - Water pollution (Box 91)
      - Radiation (Box 91)
      - Air pollution (Box 91)
    - Disease control (Box 92)
      - Communicable diseases (Box 92)
      - Venereal disease (Box 92)
      - Polio (Box 92)
      - Tuberculosis (Box 92)
      - Heart disease (Box 92)
      - Diabetes (Box 92)
      - Cancer (Box 92)
      - Conservation of vision and hearing (Box 92)
      - Arthritis (Box 92)
    - Mental health (Box 92)
    - Health education (Box 92)
    - Addiction (Box 92)
  - Clinical files
    Conditions Governing Access
    Clinical files are restricted until January 1, 2046, due to repository requirements.
    - A-H (Box 93)
    - Health PAC (Box 93)
    - Heart
      - AHA bulletins (Box 93)
      - Congenital heart disease (Box 93)
      - Coronary heart disease (Box 93)
      - Rheumatic heart disease (Box 93)
      - EKG (Box 93)
    - I-Z (Box 93)
  - Notebooks and topical files
    Notebooks and topical files are restricted until January 1, 2046, due to repository requirements.
    - Harvard School of Public Health, 1945-1948
      - Bacteriology (Box 94)
      - Biostatics/laboratory (Box 94)
      - Epidemiology (Box 94)
      - Human ecology (Box 94)
      - Maternal and child health (Box 94)
      - Medical care (Box 94)
      - Nutrition (Box 94)
      - Public health practice (Box 94)
      - Public health seminars (Box 94)
      - Sanitation (Box 94)
    - New York University, College of Medicine, 1948
      - Biostatistics (Box 94)
      - Fourth year clerkship (Box 94)
    - University of California at Los Angeles
      - Public health classes (100-B, 106, 109, 200-200A, 206 A-B, 298) (Box 94)
      - Faculty (Box 94)
      - Final report: Inter University (Box 94)
      - Los Angeles: Conference on Health and Welfare (Box 94)
      - Reading lists (Box 94)
      - Reports of activities (Box 94)
      - Students, graduate/undergraduate (Box 94)
      - Summer Labor Institute (Box 94)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 94)
  - Grants, special purpose traineeships, and miscellaneous
    Grants, special purpose traineeships and miscellaneous files are restricted until January 1, 2046, due to repository requirements.
    - Grants
      - General, 1963-1971 (Box 95)
      - CRMP (CT. REG. MED. PROG.), 1970-1972, undated (Box 95)
      - Training grants (Box 95)
    - Special purpose traineeships
      - General, 1971-1974 (Box 95)
      - Renewal, 1969-1974 (Box 95)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Faculty biographical sketches (Box 95)
      - Students
        - Fernow, C. L. (Box 95)
        - Wyszewianski, Leon (Box 95)
        - Projects and essays (Box 95)
        - Enrollments (Box 95)
    - Miscellaneous printed material and photographs (Box 96)
    - Miscellaneous printed material and photographs (Box 97)
    - Miscellaneous printed material and photographs (Box 98)
- Additional Materials, 1962-1970; Accession 1983-M-006
  This addition consists of five inches of manuscript material. The material here includes correspondence, medical papers and miscellanea with span dates of 1962-1970 and is arranged in a single box (number 99). The addition is arranged in three sections which parallel the organization of the original donation of papers.
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence section contains letters Weinerman sent to foreign medical officials in preparation for his 1970 journey abroad. Letters of condolence sent to Yale's Department of Epidemiology and Public Health upon the tragic death of Weinerman and his wife are arranged here as is correpondence relating to the Weinerman Memorial Fund. The Meorial Fund was established by the family, friends, and colleagues of Dr. Weinerman to perpetuate his work and his memory.
    - General, 1969-1970 (Box 99, Folder 1)
    - Letters of condolence, 1970 (Box 99, Folder 2)
    - Weinerman Memorial Fund, 1970 (Box 99, Folder 3-5)
  - Addresses and Writings
    Addresses and Writings includes two papers Weinerman wrote in 1969. They focus on a topic of primary concern to Dr. Weinerman: the planning and organization of health service systems. A list of talks Weinerman delivered from 1962-1969 is also arranged here.
    - "Planning for needs and demands in health services", 1969 (Box 99, Folder 6)
    - "Research on comparative health service systems", 1969 (Box 99, Folder 7)
    - Talks--list, 1962-1969 (Box 99, Folder 8)
  - Personal Papers and Miscellanea
    Personal Papers and Miscellanea contains material presented at three memorial services held in honor of the Weinermans. Transcripts of the comments offered at these ceremonies are organized here. A copy of a petition signed by Yale faculty and students urging an international response to the terrorist bombing which killed the Weinermans is also arranged here.
    - Memorial services, 1970 (Box 99, Folder 9-11)
    - Petition, 1970 (Box 99, Folder 12)